"How to Control the Muscle Loss Side Effects
(Like “Ozempic Face”) of GLP-1 Drugs"
GLP-1 type drugs, like Ozempic,
function by making patients
feel fuller, eat less,
and hence, lose weight.
However, an important
but often overlooked factor
in these studies
of these kinds of drugs
relates to the type of weight
that’s lost.
Typically, when people
who are obese lose weight,
the decrease
in their fat-free mass,
meaning essentially
their lean mass,
including their muscles,
usually represents
about 25 percent
of their total weight loss.
So, for every 4 pounds (2 kg)
lost on the scale,
one of those pounds is not fat.
But on drugs like Ozempic,
as much as 40 percent
of the total weight lost
is that lean mass, nearly half
the pounds you’re losing.
Those on Ozempic
or tirzepatide,
a newer GLP-1 drug
sold as Zepbound,
lost about 14 pounds (6 kg)
of lean mass,
about one eighth of all
the lean mass in their body.
That’s worse than the amount
of lean mass you lose
when you have
esophageal cancer,
or head and neck cancer.
Now, some people paid
by the pharma companies
that make GLP-1-type drugs
question whether the amount
of muscle mass loss
is clinically relevant.
But these drugs cause
such rapid and significant loss
of lean mass,
that it’s comparable
to how much you’d lose
over a decade or more of aging.
The drug industry consultants
argue that even if 40 percent
of the weight lost
is lean mass,
that still means the majority,
60 percent, is fat;
so, you end up
with a better fat-to-lean ratio,
in the end.
But that’s just
on the first go-around.
Remember, most people
don’t stick to these drugs
for more than a few months,
either because
they can’t keep paying
a thousand bucks a month
for them,
or they don’t want to put up
with all the side effects,
or deal with drug shortages,
or run out of refills.
And when you stop these drugs,
we know the lost body fat
piles on back,
but there’s a concern
that any lost muscle mass
may not;
so, you then actually end up
fatter in the end.
This kind of weight cycling
has been associated
with extra fat deposition
on the body,
especially around the middle.
Using the gold-standard method,
MRI,
to directly visualize
muscle mass,
researchers found
that the more times
people cycle their weight,
the worse their body composition
appears to get.
The profound level
of lean mass loss
associated
with GLP-1 weight-loss drugs
would be expected
to have deleterious impacts
on health outcomes,
including increased frailty
and perhaps greater
long-term mortality risk,
though, this concern
remains theoretical,
since any such long-term data
have yet to be published.
The good news is there’s
something we can do about it.
Exercise, particularly
resistance exercise,
like weight training,
can cut in half or more
the proportion
of fat-free mass that is lost.
Check this out:
Based on half a dozen studies
of caloric restriction
for weight loss
(like portion control),
and the same calorie restriction
plus resistance exercise,
you can see that it appears
the non-exercising group
lost more weight.
You can guess why, though,
because without
the resistance exercise,
they lost more lean mass,
whereas the exercising group
lost nine pounds (4 kg)
apparently without losing
any lean mass.
Supervised resistance training
interventions,
up to a few times a week
for more than 10 weeks,
where all major muscle groups
are worked,
can add a few extra pounds
of lean mass.
More with weights than cardio,
more when younger,
and more in men than women.
Collectively, this evidence
supports resistance training
as an effective approach
to, at the very least,
help mitigate
the decrease in lean mass;
so, programs such as these
should be adopted without delay
in patients embarking
on Ozempic-type therapy.
What about "Ozempic face"?
The term has consumed the media
with the medication’s
rising popularity
and describes rapid weight loss
in the face
that leaves
a distorted appearance.
And I’d never even heard
of Ozempic butt.
Media reports have linked
the drug to facial aging,
but perhaps it’s not so much
the medication
as much as the potent
weight-loss effects
that leave a sagging appearance
due to the loss of fat
in the face.
While this seems logical,
the explanation cannot
fully account
for the markedly accelerated
facial aging
seen in GLP-1 drug patients.
The premature facial aging
and altered skin health
appears to be multifactorial,
involving not only the loss
of fat in the face,
but an effect on stem cells
and the production
and secretion of hormonal
and metabolic factors.
These changes compromise
the structural integrity
and barrier function
of the skin
and may lead to diminished
facial muscle mass as well,
further exacerbating
the appearance of aging.
Another side effect of rapid
weight loss is gallstones,
which is not limited
to GLP-1 drugs.
Shedding
all that excess cholesterol
stored in your fat cells
can lead to it crystallizing
in your bile like rock candy,
forming gallstones.
Something else to be
cognizant of,
but in a way,
both the muscle loss
and gallstones
may just be signs
of how effective
these drugs can be
for losing weight.
In my last video,
I talked
about the common side effects,
but as semaglutide’s
popularity soars,
rare but serious adverse effects
are emerging.
Like, what about possible
thyroid cancer, pancreatitis,
kidney problems, depression,
or suicidal thoughts?
I’ll cover all those next.